Finding Aid to the Adrienne Germain papers SSC.MS.00778
Sophia Smith Collection
Adrienne Germain papers
1964-2016
Sophia Smith Collection
Germain, Adrienne
SSC.MS.00778
3.333 linear feet (3 containers)
The Adrienne Germain papers contain the working papers of Adrienne Germain, a champion for women's health and human rights in low-income countries, including essays, research materials, and correspondence related to her work with the Ford Foundation and the International Women's Health Coalition.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Accruals
Periodic accruals may be added to the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted to Smith College by Adrienne Germain in 2016.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: professional materials and writings. The materials in each series are roughly arranged in chronological order.
Biographical Note
Throughout her career, Adrienne Germain has been a major force advancing international women's health and human rights in low income countries, and has made this work central to the missions of many international organizations. Born in San Francisco in 1947 to William and Carel Germain, Germain graduated from Wellesley College in 1969 with a B.A. and from University of California at Berkeley in 1971 with an M.A., both in sociology. Germain began her career at the Population Council in 1970, where for two years she undertook family planning program research. She started work with the Ford Foundation in 1972, where she became the youngest and first woman to be appointed as a Resident Representative to Bangladesh. In this role she worked to shift discussion of population issues to a reproductive health lens. She rose to the role of Vice President of and Program Director for the International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) in 1985, where she drove policy analysis and conceptual development, supervised numerous programs and local groups in Asia, Africa, and Latin America addressing women's reproductive health rights, produced scholarship, and advised the U.S. State Department, NGOs, European governments, and the U.N. system. By 1994, Germaine's influence had led to the consensus that women's sexual and reproductive health rights were central to women's human rights, sustainable development, and population stabilization. In 1998, with the retirement of Joan Banks Dunlop, Germain became president of the IWHC. She went on to work for United Nations Population Fund as a consultant for their Reproductive Health Branch from 2011-2014. Germain has received many prestigious awards, among them the United Nations Population Award in 2012 and an Honorary Doctorate of Humane Letters at Bard College in 2001.
Related Materials
Carel B. Germain Papers. Joan Dunlop Papers. Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains materials related to Adrienne Germain's work with the Ford Foundation and the International Women's Health Coalition, including essays, research materials, and correspondence. The collection also contains awards and honors received at school and later in Germain's career, as well as photographs and notes from colleagues and friends.
Women's rights -- Developing countries -- History -- Sources; Women's rights -- South America -- History -- Sources; Women, Black -- Health and hygiene -- Africa -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Women's health services; Population policy -- History; Resumes; Research; Publications; CD-Roms; Women's rights--Asia, Southeastern--History--Sources; Essays; Reproductive health--Developing countries; Population assistance--Developing countries; Germain, Adrienne; Dunlop, Joan; Germain, Carel B.; International Women's Health Coalition; Germain, Adrienne
- Professional, 1954-2016; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Adrienne Germain's professional records. Included in this series are correspondence, memos and reports from Germain's time with the Ford Foundation as a Program Officer. Researchers can also find reports and publications, advocacy materials, history and correspondence from Germain's subsequent tenure as President of the International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC).
  Additionally, this series includes speeches and presentations by Germain, academic degrees and honors, and materials surrounding recognition of Germain's work by the UN and the White House (State Department). The series also contains selected photos and notes of Germain and IWHC staff and other colleagues and friends. Additional records related to Germain's publications and research can be found in writings.
  - Gamble, Richard -- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) History, 1954-2008 (Box 1)
  - Academic Degrees and Honors, 1964-2012 (Box 1)
  - Selected Photos and Notes, 1966-2012 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation 1, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation 2, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation 3, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation 4, 1979-1985 (Box 1)
  - CV and Correspondence, 1985-2016 (Box 1)
  - International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) Advocacy Materials, 1987-2015 (Box 1)
  - History/Evaluations by Dixon-Mueller, 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) Reports and Publications, 1989-1995 (Box 1)
  - International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) Reports and Publications 2, 1998-2004 (Box 1)
  - Joan Dunlop Comments to/about Germain and Retirement, 1991-2004 (Box 1)
  - World Health Organization (WHO) and International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) Reports, 1991-2015 (Box 1)
  - Health, Empowerment, Rights, and Accountability (HERA), 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Press Coverage of International Conference of Population and Development, 1994 (Box 1)
  - International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) Advocacy Folder, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Recognition by United Nations and White House, 1994-2013 (Box 1)
  - United Nations Negotiating "Tools", 1994-2015 (Box 1)
  - State Department Certificate of Appreciation, 1994 (Box SSC Shared 1)
  - Substantive Work to Influence Other Agencies, 1997-2011 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Presentations, 1999-2016; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Adrienne Germain: Women's Health and Human Rights, Chautauqua Institution, 2011 Jul 25; 1 items (1 CD); .665 Gigabytes (18 digital audio files) (Box 1)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
  - Germain's Departure from International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC), 2011 (Box 1)
  - United Nations Presentation Award Presentation, 2012 (Box 1)
  - United Nations Population Award, 2012 (Box SSC Shared 1)
  - Essay on International Women's Health Coalition's (IWHC) Intellectual Contribution on Sexual and Reproductive Rights and Health, 2016 (Box 1)
- Writings, 1987-2016; 2
  This series contains Germain's records pertaining to her journal articles, papers and research. Materials include papers, articles, journals and interviews edited or written by Germain, an Oral History transcript, research on women and Reproductive Justice, and articles by Ruth Dixon-Miller, a frequent co-collaborator with Germain. The series also includes numerous books, most of which were edited or include a section by Germain, or pertain to her research. Further research and publications, especially related to Germain's time at the Ford Foundation or International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC), can be found in the professional series.
  - Papers by Germain, 1987-2012 (Box 2)
  - Publications by Ruth Dixon-Mueller, 1988-2010 (Box 2)
  - Publications Edited by Germain, 1989-1994 (Box 2)
  - Publications by Ruth Dixon-Mueller and Adrienne Germain, 1992-2015 (Box 2)
  - Articles on Women and Reproductive Justice, 1997-2015 (Box 2)
  - Oral History Sharpless Transcript, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Articles and Interviews by Germain, 2005-2015 (Box 2)
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) Sex Education Report, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Profiles of Germain, 2011-2015 (Box 2)
  - Seeds, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Tract Infections, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Population Policy and Women's Rights, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Beyond the Numbers, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Contraceptive Research and Development, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Population and Reproductive Rights, 1994 (Box 2)
  - A Commitment to the World's Women, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Women's Empowerment and Demographic Processes, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Issues in Women's Health and Rights, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health and Human Rights, 2009 (Box 2)
  - A Pivotal Moment, 2010 (Box 2)
  - Women and Girls Rising, 2016 (Box 2)
  - Global Public Health, Volume 10, Numbers 1-2, 2016 (Box 2)